Inventory of the Dromgoole Family Papers 1821-1896, 1850-1890
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Dromogoole Papers, 1821-1896, 1850-1890.
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Mss. 39.1 D83
96 items, 13 volumes.
The collection includes papers of W. E. Dromgoole; and papers concerning the estates of George Coke Dromgoole and Edward Dromgoole, Jr. (d. ca. 1848).
Edward Dromgoole, fl. 1838-1897,; George Coke Dromgoole, 1797-1847,; Edward Dromgoole Jr., d. ca. 1848,; W. E. Dromgoole.
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
96 items, 13 volumes.
Biographical/Historical Information
The Dromgoole family resided in Brunswick County, Va. Edward Dromgoole was a follower of John Wesley and a minister for sixty years, dying in 1835 at the age of 84. His son George C. Dromgoole served in the Virginia House of Delegates and State Senate. He also served in U.S. House of Representatives 1835-1841 and 1843-1847. A family member named Edward Dromgoole was a merchant and lawyer in Brunswick County and a person by that name served in the Virginia General Assembly, 1855-1858.
Scope and Content Information
Papers, chiefly 1850-1890, including correspondence, accounts (including accounts, 1875-1895, of laborers ?) and manuscript volumes (journals, ledgers and a fee book, 1866-1878), of members of the Dromgoole family of Brunswick County, Va. Most of the manuscripts apparently were created by Edward Dromgoole (fl. 1838-1897), a merchant and lawyer of Brunswick County.
Arrangement
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged according to the series stated in the organization and then into chronological order by date.
Organization
This collection has been organized into 9 series: 1. Correspondence, 2. Accounts, bills, and receipts of Edward Dromgoole, merchant, 3. Accounts, bills, and receipts of Edward Dromgoole, attorney, 4. Accounts, bills, and receipts of W.E. Dromgoole, farmer, 5. Miscellaneous laborers' accounts, 6. Miscellaneous accounts, 7. Legal Papers, 8. Speeches, 9. Manuscript volumes.
Index Terms
Family Names:
Dromgoole family.
Persons:
Dromgoole, Edward, fl. 1838-1897.; Dromgoole, George Coke, 1797- 1847.; Dromgoole, Edward, Jr., d. ca. 1848.; Dromgoole, W. E.
Subjects:
Practice of law--Virginia--History.
Geographical Names:
Brunswick County (Va.)--History--19th century.
Occupations:
Merchants--Virginia--Brunswick County.; Merchants--Virginia--History--19th century.; Lawyers--Virginia--Brunswick County.
Components List
  Series 1: Correspondence
- Correspondence of Edward Dromgoole, merchant, 1872-[18]80, n.d., 5 items. (Box-folder 1:1)
  Correspondence and miscellany of Edward Dromgoole, [merchant of Brunswick County, Virginia?], including the following: 1872 notice of blank income tax for 1871 enclosure; 1873 announcement from Wm. Brinckerhoff & County, [New York, N.Y.] of new fall stock of hats, caps, frs, and straw goods; notices from Registrar E. Dromgoole that he will register qualified voters at Dromgoole's Store on May 11, 1880; and "Field notes of tract of land," n.d.
  Series 2: Accounts, bills, and receipts of Edward Dromgoole, merchant
- Accounts, bills, and receipts of Edward Dromgoole, merchant of Brunswick County, Virginia, 1867-1877., 11 items. (Box-folder 1:2)
  Series 3: Accounts, bills, and receipts of Edward Dromgoole, attorney
- Accounts, bills, and receipts of Edward Dromgoole, attorney of {Brunswick County, Virginia and South Gaston, North Carolina?], 184[7], 1863-1873, n.d., 11 items. (Box-folder 1:3)
  This includes the following: an account, 1871-1872, showing payment to Virginia Military Institute, of J.W. Harrison, an orphan of N.M. Harrison, of whom E. Dromgoole was guardian, and accounts in his capacity as executor of the estate of Isaac F. Harris, Sr.; also blank promissory notes, 184[7], for accounts involved with the estate of George C. Dromgoole, Edward Dromgoole, Administrator.
  Series 4: Accounts, bills, and receipts of W.E. Dromgoole, farmer
- Accounts, bills, and receipts of W.E. Dromgoole, farmer, of "Westward" and "Lizard Creek" plantations in [North Carolina?], 1866-1876., 23 items. (Box-folder 1:4)
  These included the following: those of a saw mill; also cotton accounts.
  Series 5: Miscellaneous laborer's accounts
- Miscellaneous [laborer's accounts?], 1875-1895, n.d., 8 items. (Box-folder 1:5)
  These include the following: share listings written on the back of "E. Dromgoole, Attorney at Law" letterhead, 189_.
  Series 6: Miscellaneous accounts,
- Miscellaneous accounts, bills, and receipts, 1821-1882, n.d., 15 items. (Box-folder 1:6)
  These include the following: a Brunswick County, Virginia tax receipt of Lucretia Atkins, 1821, listing 148 acres land, 4 slaves over [the age] of 16 years, and a two-wheeled riding carriage, and signed by Edward Dromgoole; and a Brunswick County, Virginia tax receipt, 1845, of Jos[eph] Cain, signed by G[eorge]C. Dromgoole.
  Series 7: Legal papers
- Legal papers, 1858-1896, n.d., 5 items. (Box-folder 1:7)
  These include the following: will of J.W. Palmer, Northhampton County, North Carolina, 26 November 1858; letter to E. Dromgoole, Esq., 1872, concerning the rights of a widow; notice, 1878, of an auction of [L.J. Pearman's ?], deceased, perishable estate; letter 1896, giving information regarding deeds for lands in Amelia and Jeffress, and the Mountain Hall tract; and blank printed form for the "Sale of real Estate in Brunswick County, Virginia"
  Series 8: Speeches,
- Speeches, 1865-1872, n.d., 3 items. (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Eulogy written and/or delivered by [Edward Dromgoole], [post February 1865.], 4 pages. Ms. (Box-folder 1:8)
    This item was written and/or delivered upon the death of a fellow attorney from Brunswick County, Virginia, John E. Shell,
  - Speech of [Edward Dromgoole, announcing his support for Horace Greeley for President,] [ante nov. 1872]., 6 pages. Ms. (Box-folder 1:8)
    This item also [states that Ulysses S.] Grant "does not fill the measure and standard of what an American President ought to be in the public eye at home and abroad."
  - Rough drafts of speeches of [Edward Dromgoole] on the topic of agriculture and its various aspects, n.d., 11 pp. Ms. (Box-folder 1:8)
  Series 9: Manuscript Volumes
- Manuscript volumes, 1838-1896., 15 items. (Box 1-2)
  - Ledger of [Edward Dromgoole?], merchant of Brunswick County, Virginia, 1838-1856., 381 pages. MsV. (Box-folder 1:9)
    This includes the following: accounts connected with the estate settlements of Geo[rge] C. Dromgoole, 1847-1853; Edward Dromgoole, Jr., 1848-1856; and Sarah C. Dromgoole, 1848-1849, with Edward Dromgoole, executor or administrator for all cases.
  - Journal and ledger of [Edward Dromgoole?], merchant of Brunswick County, Virginia, 1865-1866., 244 pp. MsV. (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Journal of [Edward Dromgoole?], 1866, 1887-1891., 387 pages. MsV. (Box-folder 2:1)
    This item includes farm accounts with "Westward" and "Lizzard Creek" plantations [in North Carolina?], records of ginning and baling cotton, 1866-1870; a diagram of an orchard containing apple, peach, and pear trees; and a schedule of gold prices in Confederate money, 1861-1865.
  - Ledger of [Edward Dromgoole?], merchant of Brunswick County, Virginia, 1866-1873., 308 pages. MsV. Including index. (Box-folder 2:2)
    This item includes accounts of the orphans of N.M. Harrison at "Lizzard Creek" and "Westward" plantations [North Carolina?].
  - Fee book of Edward Dromgoole, attorney, 1866-1878., 92 pages. Includes index. (Box-folder 2:3)
    This item contains ledger information for services rendered; includes lists of judgements docketed in Brunswick Circuit, n.d.; Halifax Circuit Court, 1867; Greensville County; Petersburg Circuit Court, 1866.
  - Daybook of [Edward Dromgoole?], merchant of Brunswick County, Virginia, 1867-1870., 473 pages. MsV. See Oversize manuscripts Volumes File. (Box-folder 2:4)
    This item includes a list of books in the store, 3 April 1867.
  - Journal of [Edward Dromgoole?], merchant of Brunswick County, Virginia, 1871-1873., 405 pages. MsV. (Box-folder 2:5)
    This item includes a recipe for hair oil.
  - Ledger of [Edward Dromgoole?], merchant of Brunswick County, Virginia, 1873-1879., 261 pages. MsV. Also including index. (Box-folder 3:1)
    This item includes accounts of the "orphans of N.M. Harrison."
  - E. Dromgoole's "Cotton Book", 1879-1896., 183 pages. MsV. (Box-folder 3:2)
    This item contains cotton accounts, including records of cotton baled, ginned, and prepared. Also including accounts, 1895-1896, of the estate of E. Dromgoole, Edward Dromgoole and George C. Dromgoole, administrators.
  - "Ledger A" of [Edward Dromgoole?], merchant of Brunswick County, Virginia, 1880-1897., 312 pages. MsV. Including index. (Box-folder 3:3)
  - Journal of [Edward Dromgoole?], merchant of Brunswick County, Virginia, 1885-1887., 203 pages. MsV. (Box-folder 3:4)
  - Ledger of [Edward Dromgoole?], merchant of Brunswick County, Virginia, 1885-1889., 219 pages. MsV. Including index. (Box-folder 4:1)
  - Ledger of [W.E. Dromgoole?], Brunswick County, Virginia, 1887-1889., 232 pages. MsV. Including index. (Box-folder 4:2)
    This item contains saw mill, cotton, and farm accounts.
  - Ledger "C" of [Edward Dromgoole?], merchant of Brunswick County, Virginia, 1889-1895., 228 page. MsV. Including index. (Box-folder 4:3)
  - Journal of [Edward Dromgoole?], merchant of Brunswick County, Virginia, 1891-1896., 260 page. MsV. (Box-folder 4:4)